[SITARA] Simply put,
you and Emperor Ögedei
have filled me
with a sense of hope.
[Boraqchin gasps]
[SITARA] The great wisdom
you both display
makes you worthy
of ruling this world
with honor and grace. Yes.
[tearfully]
Do you really think so?
Of course I do.
[BORAQCHIN] There's no need
for you to feel so nervous.
I just have something
I wanted to discuss with you.
♪
-[indistinct chatter]
-[grunting]
♪
[ILÜGE] Good tidings,
Great Kha'an.
Tolui has crossed the Han River.
And the enemy troops
have begun scurrying southward.
Tolui, you've done well.
All right, let's make our move,
and cross the river ahead.
[♪ opening theme song playing]
So, my brother has crossed
the Yellow River?
Yes. Reinforcements from
the Great Kha'an are coming.
We should muster.
That does seem wise.
Well, do you know
of a good location?
[SUBUTAI] Mount Sanfeng
will serve us well.
♪
[SITARA (ADULT)] 130 kilometers
from Kaifeng, the Jin capital.
Tolui's army began positioning
themselves
at the foot of Mount Sanfeng,
awaiting the arrival
of reinforcements.
Though, the opposing Jin army
seemed ready
to confront them and wage war.
[Wanyan exhales]
[WANYAN] You bring orders
to launch an attack now?
My men are thoroughly exhausted.
I'm sure our enemy is as well.
The bulk of their main force
has its sights set
on the capital.
[Wanyan gasps, grunts]
Do away with their troops
at once.
[cart rattling]
What shall we do?
Follow his orders.
Fortunately,
we outnumber the enemy.
So, we'll encircle them all.
[Tolui sighs]
They have us
completely surrounded.
There are 150,000 troops,
at least.
Oh, really? And our count?
Under 40,000.
-[laughs]
-Uh?
It is no laughing matter, sir.
If the Great Kha'an's
reinforcements
don't make it in time,
we're done for.
They will, so there's no need
for concern.
-[all groaning]
-[neighs]
[commander sighs]
Fine. Then...
how about we entrust
our fate to Tengri?
What?
Hmm. Bring me a soldier
who can perform
the jadamishi rite.
[COMMANDER]
The jadamishi is known
to summon storms, isn't it?
What is it he hopes to
accomplish by doing this rite?
[Subutai sighs]
♪
[squawking]
[all gasp softly]
-Now it's...
-Snowing.
And the wind's picked up.
♪
Tengri...
So you have agreed
to grant our wish.
[footsteps]
[TOLUI] Listen up, men!
Start digging trenches at once!
Have all the men
and horses take cover
before the storm arrives!
Cover those horses in blankets.
Our soldiers need to be
bundled up!
[wind howling]
[SITARA (ADULT)] The storm raged
for three days and nights.
[grunting]
[SITARA (ADULT)]
Swaying the fates
of the two forces
through perilous weather.
And then on the fourth day,
the 150,000 strong Jin army...
[Tolui laughs]
... subjected to cold
and fatigue in their haste...
[continues laughing]
[inhales, grunts]
[horses snorting, neighing]
[SITARA (ADULT)]
...found themselves powerless
against the Mongol offensive.
[Tolui grunts]
Fire!
[men grunting]
[SITARA (ADULT)]
And were annihilated.
♪
[men grunting]
We must return...
back to the capital.
[grunting]
♪
Made it just in time.
[Wanyan gasps]
Dear Brother!
Tolui.
-You really did it, didn't you?
-I did nothing.
It was Tengri
who favored your flag
throughout our battle.
[ÖGEDEI] Still...
I'm so blessed that
you're my younger brother.
[Tolui gasps softly]
[chuckles]
You all right, General?
I'm just thinking
about the past.
Back when Genghis Khan
was at war
with the other
steppe tribe leaders,
the enemy performed
the jadamishi rite.
But the storm didn't break over
Genghis Khan and his troops.
It fell upon the enemy's forces.
♪
Now, when I look
at Prince Tolui,
-it's almost as if he...
-[COMMANDER] General...
Maybe we ought
to leave it at that.
[SUBUTAI] Hm. Forget it.
♪
[SITARA (ADULT)]
After winter had passed,
and spring was at its end,
Ögedei and Tolui set out on
their journey back to Mongolia.
Entrusting the capture
of Kaifeng
to their most trusted
veteran generals.
And they were enough
to do the job.
Only two years after this,
the Jin dynasty
would come to an end.
♪
[TOLUI] At this rate,
we'll be back in no time!
Seems the circle hunt strategy
was quite a success.
That right, Boroldai?
Name's still Otai, Father.
[TEMÜGE] Hmm.
And while I didn't lose out
in the end,
I didn't exactly gain much,
either.
- [laughs]
- [TEMÜGE] I wonder
who benefitted the most from it.
♪
[KIRGISTANI] Huh?
Congratulations
on your great victory.
[Ögedei grunts]
Glad to see you're looking
so well, Boraqchin.
I have acquired a gift for you.
It should be arriving soon.
-I think you'll be pleased.
-Huh?
[BORAQCHIN] Mmm.
We've made banquet preparations.
Please come this way.
[exclaims] Say, Great Kha'an.
What's this gift?
Is there one for me?
-[laughs] Why, of course.
-Oh! What could it be?
[Töregene exhales]
[SITARA] Huh?
[Shira chuckles]
Shira!
Hey, it's been a while.
What are you doing here?
I'm going to be serving
Prince Tolui for a bit.
Princess's orders.
♪
[indistinct chatter, laughter]
So, brother, which land
shall we invade next?
I'd prefer to build
a capital first.
-Fatima.
-Yes, my Lady Töregene?
You can take your leave
for the evening.
And when I'm in my tent,
don't disturb me.
[SITARA] Uh?
[SITARA] Lady Töregene...
doesn't really say much to me
at all anymore.
It almost seems like
she's avoiding me.
Now I'm not to disturb her
in her tent.
[gasps]
♪
[Sitara gasps]
The Great Kha'an?
[SITARA (ADULT)]
Just as Ögedei and Tolui
were returning back
to their own territories,
partway through...
[Ögedei breathes heavily]
Great Kha'an? [gasps]
Great Kha'an! Rein in, men!
Are you in pain? What is it?
Great Kha'an?
Someone fetch a physician!
[SITARA (ADULT)]
... Emperor Ögedei
was suddenly struck down
by a mysterious illness.
[Kirgistani crying]
Great Kha'an!
I'm certain he's just tired
from the long journey.
-It will be all right, I'm sure.
-Oh, that poor man!
[Kirgistani continues crying]
[SITARA] What is it?
This ominous feeling.
Something doesn't feel right.
[MÖGE] Slave girl.
Come with me.
It seems the Great Kha'an
was poisoned.
Poisoned?
And it's not just
my false belief this time.
-Boraqchin said so herself.
-[breathes shakily]
Listen to me, you are the one
who saved
Mistress Boraqchin's life.
Which is why
I don't want to doubt you.
What do you mean by that?
The Great Kha'an's symptoms
are the same as Boraqchin's.
He was poisoned
with Rahj al-gar.
-[Sitara gasps]
-What's more...
The Rahj al-gar
in Boraqchin's possession
has suddenly disappeared.
Only a few souls knew about it,
and where it was located.
Lady Möge, I swear
I don't know anything
about what happened!
I would never aim to take
the Great Kha'an's life--
What a great relief!
It really wasn't you!
Huh? But I haven't made
my case yet.
Nah, I wouldn't understand.
It's fine.
But you know...
Though I am not
the brightest person,
I can tell pretty well whether
someone is lying to me or not.
[SITARA] Uh?
Are you lost again?
[SITARA] Hm?
[SITARA] Mm...
[MÖGE] Hey! I can see
the doubt on your face!
But still,
if it really wasn't you,
then that would mean
it was Töregene.
[Sitara gasps]
[breathes uneasily]
[both grunt]
♪
[breathes shakily]
[MÖGE] Slave girl.
Töregene turned out to have
the Rahj al-gar.
[gasps]
She's being held prisoner
while they investigate.
[SITARA] Lady Töregene...
It can't be. How?
Is this some sort of plot?
Listen, slave girl,
I have a favor to ask of you.
[Sitara gasps]
[SITARA] Uh?
Empress Boraqchin's ger?
Go in.
Pardon the intrusion. Uh?
[BORAQCHIN] Fatima...
Thank you both for coming.
[Ögedei breathes shakily]
I've requested your presence
for one reason.
I would like for you
to save the Great Kha'an.
[SITARA]
What do the physicians say?
Who knows?
Töregene may very well
have conspired with a physician.
At the present time,
we can't be certain
who is trustworthy or not.
I beg of you. Help him.
[SITARA] His symptoms...
They're the same as yours,
when you were poisoned
by Rahj al-gar.
It's safe to assume that
he has been poisoned as well.
I've already used
more than half of the stone.
If you'll allow,
I'll serve you as your
new Jada stone, Highness.
Empress Boraqchin,
may I ask you one thing?
-What is it?
-Lady Töregene...
Why would she want
to poison him?
I see. Töregene was
your mistress, wasn't she?
I imagine this comes
as a great shock to you.
-However...
-[gasps]
That woman is a complete fool!
She has openly shown resentment
toward the Great Kha'an
time and time again.
And upon gaining your wisdom,
she was driven
to commit this foul act.
I'm sure it was her intention
to lay all the blame onto you,
and evade justice herself.
That can't be true!
I don't believe it.
How can you be so sure?
Because... she wouldn't do that.
After all, she was willing
to tell me about everything.
Everything...
that she'd kept sealed away
in her heart.
Even of the people
she'd once loved.
And the anger
she bears to this day.
Is that really so?
[gasps] Huh?
Fatima, you served Sorghaghtani
before you came here, yes?
Töregene is hardly so naive
that she would trust you
as easily as that,
knowing who you
previously served?
Now think back carefully, girl.
Is there anything
she could have done
that you might have found
remotely suspicious?
[SITARA] Did Lady Töregene
really do this?
Empress Boraqchin...
Please grind up this stone
and have the Great Kha'an
take some every day.
If you end up running out,
please find another Jada stone.
One with a similar color
to this stone if possible.
[both gasp]
-You have my gratitude.
-[chuckles]
[grunts] Brother has fallen ill?
So how is he faring?
Is it curable?
[SHIRA] It is unknown
what disease has befallen him.
But physicians
from east and west
have convened to tend to him.
I hear he is already
showing signs of recovery.
Really?
Great Khatun Boraqchin
has called for kams
to perform an exorcism.
And asks that you attend
as well, Highness.
-[TOLUI] I'll go at once!
-[gasps] Wait, Tolui!
[TOLUI] Uh?
Sorghaghtani?
He suddenly fell ill?
Something doesn't seem right.
Shira, what did Fatima say?
She told me...
There are many
who won't take kindly
to relying solely
on foreign physicians.
Which is why they're adhering
to Mongol tradition
by performing an exorcism.
At least, that's what
I have been told.
Well, that makes sense.
Tell Princess Sorghaghtani this.
[SHIRA] Huh?
Please do not fret.
Empress Boraqchin
is quite clever,
and she is worthy
of being trusted. [chuckles]
[SORGHAGHTANI] It's true.
I've heard tell of how clever
Boraqchin Khatun is.
You worry too much,
Sorghaghtani.
'Cause after all,
it is merely an exorcism.
Tengri has always sided
with my brother
in his past battles.
I'm quite sure...
Tengri will protect him now too.
Yes.
[Tolui grunts]
Oh.
[SORGHAGHTANI]
"It is merely an exorcism."
I suppose that's true.
I'll have to put my faith
in Fatima's words.
[indistinct chatter]
[MAN 1]
The Great Kha'an has fallen ill?
I've heard rumors
someone put a curse on him.
Hush! You mustn't speak
so frivolously about curses.
-[chatter continues]
-[SITARA] Lady Töregene...
I wish I could talk to you
right now.
Perhaps this is my best chance,
amidst all this commotion.
[chatter continues indistinctly]
[Ögedei breathes heavily]
The malevolent spirits
have now been sealed away
in the water within this bowl.
The guardian spirits
have spoken,
and they tell us
that saving the patient
will require a sacrifice
in his stead.
One of you must drink
every last drop of this water.
[all gasp]
Then allow me to do it.
[Möge gasps]
[BORAQCHIN]
I'm past my prime already.
[KAM] Please wait a moment.
A blood relative would make
for a better sacrifice.
What now?
A child or grandchild
of the Great Kha'an
would certainly suffice.
Or perhaps...
A brother of his?
[all gasp]
Well then, it's me.
Uncle.
♪
[TOLUI] Oh, Tengri...
If it is for my brother's sins
that you have made away
with his soul,
then you already know of a soul
with deeper sins than his.
For it is I who have taken
many more lives,
and plundered more than he has.
But wait, hold on.
What if he was actually summoned
for his talents,
to faithfully serve
at Tengri's side?
Well, then.
I'm still the better choice.
[all breathe uneasily]
♪
[Tolui gulping]
[Tolui sighs]
♪
[♪ closing theme song playing]
[SITARA (ADULT)]
Next time: "Wisdom."